History, Department of; Records ua615
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Department of History Records
1962-2018
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
ua615
5.22 cubic ft.
The Department of History Records contains documents related to the Bachelor of Arts degree, a Doctor of Philosophy degree, a Masters of Arts Degree, and a Certificate of Advanced Study in Public History. Documents also relate to the changing thematic and geographic focus of various degree tracks.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Web Archives
Access
Faculty meeting minutes are restricted due to the presence of personnel information and access must be permitted by the University Archivist and the Department of History. The other portions of the collection are open for use.
Acquisition Information
All items in this collection were transfered to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives. The collection began with a transfer from former faculty member Harry S. Price. This includes the subject files and memoranda and the pre-1990 meeting minutes. Price's personal records were split off into the Harry Price Papers. An additional accession in 2019 transfered the syllabi and post-1990 minutes.
Administrative History
This collection contains material that relates to the establishment and/or retrenchment of the PhD Program, various social studies degrees and the Public History Program. The Doctoral Program in History was established in 1965 with the rapid expansion of the school into a research university, but was de-certified in 1975 in the wake of widespread cuts. The program was reintroduced in 1992.
Scope and Contents
The Department of History Records contain correspondence, memorandums, and meeting minutes related to administrative operations. Items also include course descriptions, resource directories, and programs of various events. Interdepartmental programs with Library Science, Social Studies, and Liberal Arts are also documented. This collection also contains a Nobel Prize Nomination that was developed by a faculty member of the History Department.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized into 4 series. Series 1 and 3 arranged chronologically and series 2 and 4 arranged alphabetically.
Academic disciplines; Albany (N.Y.); Administrative records; Correspondence; Minutes; Web Archives; UAlbany Academic Departments; State University of New York at Albany
- Memoranda, 1963-2009; Undated; 0.5 cubic ft.
  Scope and Contents
  Contains departmental communications, documenting social events, guidance and opportunities for students, department news, enrollment numbers, class lists, interview schedules, and annoucements of faculty appointments.
  - Memoranda, 1963-ca.1975; Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Memoranda, 1975-1976 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Memoranda, 1976-1977 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Memoranda, 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Memoranda, 1978-1979 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Memoranda, 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Memoranda, 1980-1981 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Memoranda, 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Memoranda, 1983-1984 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Memoranda, 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Memoranda, 1985-1986 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Memoranda, 1986-1987 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Memoranda, 1987-1988 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Memoranda, 1988-1989 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Memoranda, 1989-1990 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Memoranda, 1990-2009; Undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Faculty Meeting Minutes, 1977-2013; Undated; 0.5 cubic ft.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Access to faculty meeting minuntes are restricted do to the presence of personnel information. Access to certain minutes must be approved by both the University Archives and the Department of History.
  Faculty minutes document both department policies and procedures as well as routine activities. The minutes commonly discuss course proposals, faculty appointments, general education requirements, tenure reviews, and procedures for discretionary salary increases.
  - 1977-1978 Meeting Minutes, Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Faculty meeting minutes are restricted due to the presence of personnel information and access must be permitted by the University Archivist and the Department of History.
  - 1978-1979 Meeting Minutes (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 1979-1980 Meeting Minutes (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 1980-1981 Meeting Minutes (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 1981-1982 Meeting Minutes (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 1982-1983 Meeting Minutes (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 1983-1984 Meeting Minutes (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 1984-1985 Meeting Minutes (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 1985-1986 Meeting Minutes (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 1986-1987 Meeting Minutes (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - 1987-1988 Meeting Minutes (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - 1988-1989 Meeting Minutes (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - 1989-1990 Meeting Minutes, Undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - 1990-1991 Meeting Minutes (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - 1991-1992 Meeting Minutes (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - 1992-1993 Meeting Minutes (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - 1993-1994 Meeting Minutes (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - 1994-1995 Meeting Minutes, Undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - 1995-1996 Meeting Minutes, Undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - 1996-1997 Meeting Minutes (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - 1997-1998 Meeting Minutes (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - 1998-1999 Meeting Minutes (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - 1999-2000 Meeting Minutes, Undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - 2000-2001 Meeting Minutes, 1997-2001; Undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - 2001-2002 Meeting Minutes (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - 2002-2003 Meeting Minutes (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - 2003-2004 Meeting Minutes (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - 2004-2005 Meeting Minutes (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - 2005-2006 Meeting Minutes (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - 2006-2007 Meeting Minutes (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - 2007-2008 Meeting Minutes, Undated (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - 2008-2009 Meeting Minutes, 2003; Undated (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - 2009-2010 Meeting Minutes (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - 2010-2011 Meeting Minutes, Undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - 2011-2012 Meeting Minutes (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - 2012-2013 Meeting Minutes, Undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - 2013-2014 Meeting Minutes, 2009-2010; 2012-2013; Undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Syllabi, 1965-2018; 3.33 cubic ft.
  Contains syllabi used for undergraduate and graduate history courses, which show an outline of the course schedule, readings, assignments, and course policies such as plagarism.
  - Syllabi, 1965 Summer (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Syllabi, 1967 Fall (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Syllabi, 1989 Spring (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Syllabi - Undergraduate, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Syllabi - Graduate, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Syllabi, 1993 Spring (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Syllabi, 1993 Fall (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Syllabi, 1994 Spring (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Syllabi, 1994 Summer (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Syllabi, 1994 Fall (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Syllabi, 1995 Spring (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Syllabi, 1995 Summer (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Syllabi, 1995 Fall (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Syllabi, 1996 Spring (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Syllabi, 1996 Summer (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Syllabi, 1996 Fall (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Syllabi, 1997 Spring (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Syllabi, 1997 Summer (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Syllabi, 1997 Fall (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Syllabi, 1998 Spring (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Syllabi, 1998 Summer (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Syllabi, 1998 Fall (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Syllabi, 1999 Spring (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Syllabi, 1999 Summer (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Syllabi, 1999 Fall (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Syllabi, 2000 Spring (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Syllabi, 2000 Summer (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Syllabi, 2000 Fall (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Syllabi, 2001 Spring (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Syllabi, 2001 Summer (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Syllabi, 2001 Fall (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Syllabi, 2002 Spring (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Syllabi, 2002 Summer (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Syllabi, 2002 Fall (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Syllabi, 2003 Spring (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Syllabi, 2003 Summer (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Syllabi, 2003 Fall (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Syllabi, 2004 Spring (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Syllabi, 2004 Summer (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Syllabi, 2004 Fall (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Syllabi, 2005 Spring (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Syllabi, 2005 Summer (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Syllabi, 2005 Fall (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Syllabi, 2006 Spring (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Syllabi, 2006 Summer (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Syllabi, 2006 Fall (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Syllabi, 2007 Spring (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Syllabi, 2007 Summer (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Syllabi, 2007 Fall (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Syllabi, 2008 Spring (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Syllabi, 2008 Summer (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Syllabi (1 of 2), 2008 Fall (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Syllabi (2 of 2), 2008 Fall (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Syllabi, 2009 Spring (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Syllabi, 2009 Summer (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Syllabi (1 of 2), 2009 Fall (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Syllabi (2 of 2), 2009 Fall (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Syllabi, 2010 Spring (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Syllabi, 2010 Fall (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Syllabi, 2011 Fall (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Syllabi, 2012 Fall (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Syllabi, 2013 Fall (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Syllabi, 2014 Fall (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Syllabi, 2015 Fall (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Syllabi, 2016 Fall (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Syllabi, 2017 Fall (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Syllabi, 2018 Fall (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Syllabi, 2019 Fall (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Syllabi, 2020 Fall (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Syllabi, 2021 Fall (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Syllabi, 2022 Fall (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Syllabi, 2023 Fall (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Syllabi, 2024 Fall (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Syllabi, 2025 Fall (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Syllabi, 2016 Spring (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Syllabi, 2016 Fall (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Syllabi, 2017 Winter (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Syllabi, 2017 Spring (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Syllabi, 2017 Fall (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Syllabi, 2018 Fall (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Subject Files, 1962-2003; Undated; .89 cubic ft.
  Contains publications, guides, forms and summaries from the University and the College of Arts & Sciences, programs for commencement and other events, correspondence, self-evaluations, department planning, alumni newsletters, course descriptions and proposal, department and affiliated department undergraduate and graduate academic program development handouts, and the materials provided for the nomination of Raoul Wallenberg for the 1982 Nobel Prize.
  - "1979-80 Undergraduate Bulletin Material" (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "B.A. /M.A. in History, ca. 1981" Proposal (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Chairman, Dean, and Administration Correspondence, 1968; 1973; 1976 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - College of Arts and Sciences Faculty Viewsletters, 1995-1996 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Cosponsored Events and Programs, 1988; 2002 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Course Descriptions, 1976; 2000 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Crippen Prize, 1969; Undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Department Graduation Booklet, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Dr. H. Peter Krosby's 1982 Nobel Prize Nomination of Raoul Wallenberg Materials (Flat-file 1)
  - Dr. H. Peter Krosby's 1982 Nobel Prize Nomination of Raoul Wallenberg Materials (1 of 2), 1982-1989; 1991; 1999-2000; Undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Dr. H. Peter Krosby's 1982 Nobel Prize Nomination of Raoul Wallenberg Materials (2 of 2), 1982-1989; 1991; 1999-2000; Undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - "Encouraging Teacher Education May 1990 and Notes to Jim Mancuso 3/91", 1989-1990; Undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - "Gen. Ed. Forms and Programs", ca. 1982-ca. 1984 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - History Department Program Handouts, ca. 1967-2003; Undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - "History Department Search for Department Chairman 1967-1968", Undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - History Newsletter Alumnae Notes and Activities, 1978-1983; ca. 1989-ca.1990; Undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - History Newsletter Alumnae Notes and Activities, 1978-1983; ca. 1989-ca.1990; Undated (Flat-file 2)
  - History Newsletter Copies, Mailing Lists, and Edits, 1983-1984; 1987-1988; Undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - History Newsletter Correspondences Between Kendall Birr, Faculty, and Alumnae, 1978; 1981; 1983-1989; Undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Navigator Lists and Floppy Disks, 1992; Undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Past and Present Newsletter with Article, 2003; Undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Perspectives on Empire State History Materials, 1999; 2002-2003; Undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Ph.D Program Proposals and Development, 1963; 1968; 1975; Undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Phi Alpha Theta Lecture Booklets, 1982; 1986; 1990-1999 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Robert S. Leventhal 1986 Symposium Paper, ca. 1986 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - "Self Study Document", 1981 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - "Social Studies: Catalog Statements 1983-84", 1983-1984 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Social Studies (Non-Teaching) Master's Program Correspondence and Materials, 1977-1978; 1981; Undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Social Studies and American Studies Annual Reports, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Social Studies Program Planning, 1973; 1975-1979; 1986; Undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - "Social Studies Teacher Ed. Planning/Middle States 1989-1990", Undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - "Social Studies Teacher Education Competency Based Teacher Education", 1974; 1977; Undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Social Studies Teacher Education Program Changes, 1969; 1971-1972; 1977-1979; Undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - "SST/Teacher Ed. 1990 Future of Advisement, Draft of the Committee on Education", 1988; 1990-1991; Undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - SUNY and University at Albany Publications, 1986; 1991; 2000-2001 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Syracuse University Maxwell School of Citizenship and Public Affairs Newsletter, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Three-Year Development Plan, 1976-1977; 1979 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - "Transfer Agreements Community Colleges", 1986-1987 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Transfer Guides 1993-1994 (1 of 2) (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Transfer Guides 1993-1994 (2 of 2) (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Transfer Guides 1999 and 2001-2002 (1 of 3) (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Transfer Guides 1999 and 2001-2002 (2 of 3) (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Transfer Guides 1999 and 2001-2002 (3 of 3) (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Transfer Guide with Columbia Greene Community College, Undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Undergraduate Teaching Requirement, 1983-1984 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - University at Albany Executive Summaries, 1983-1984 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Web Archives, 1997 June 7-2016 September 18; nam_ua615-1; 787 captures
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  Web crawling is managed through the Internet Archive's Archive-It service. This page includes links to both the university's collection and the Internet Archive's public collection.
  Surface-level crawling of www.albany.edu is performed daily which should includes most top-level webpages. Separate targeted crawls of every albany.edu subdomain are performed monthly to attempt to gather all content. This includes: www.albany.edu, www.rna.albany.edu, www.ctg.albany.edu, www.ualbanysports.com, www.albany.edu/rockefeller, www.albany.edu/cela, www.albany.edu/asrc, m.albany.edu, library.albany.edu, events.albany.edu, cstar.cestm.albany.edu, csda.albany.edu, and alumni.albany.edu
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
  Web Archives
  The departmental website was used for promoting the department's programs to potential students and for news and reference information for current students and faculty.
  - http://www.albany.edu/history/ - University Archives collection, 2013 May 8-2016 September 18 (Web-archive 1)
  - WARC file for http://www.albany.edu/history/, (please see https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Web_ARChive for more details), 2013 May 8-2016 September 18 (Warc 1)
    WARC files are very large and difficult to work with. Your request may take time to process, and we may be unable to deliver your request remotely. Please consult an archivist if you are interested in researching with web archives.
  - http://www.albany.edu/history/ - Internet Archive collection, 1997 June 7-2016 September 18 (Web-archive 2)